בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ס"ו, Samech Vav, 66,
but we're actually a good deal ahead, so we'll probably be a
דף daf ahead by the end of today. We pick up at
the bottom of ס"ו עמוד ב'. Samech Vav Amud Bet. We just
did this whole debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים
Chachamim of חקקו ולבסוף חיברו. chakako ulbesof chibro. If you have a
כלי, kli, a vessel, that you then attach to the ground, how
much is it considered part of the ground, and does it have
the status of a כלי kli for aspects of טומאה tumah and
other aspects as well? מקוה, mikvah, is it part of the house,
selling the house with it and so on,
where there's a middle position which is if you first attach it
and then make it a כלי, kli, it is part of the
ground, if you make it a כלי kli then attach, it retains
its status of a כלי. kli. That's like a good logical middle
position. But the גמרא Gemara also framed the two extremes, that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it always becomes part of the ground once
you attach it, and that was relevant like if you sell the
house, you sell it with the things that have been attached to
the ground, but also relevant for other הלכות halachot of טומאה, tumah,
of impurity, of מקוה mikvah issues and so on. What?
Right. And the חכמים Chachamim say the opposite, that even if you
first attached and then carved it out, it would be considered a
כלי. kli. So those were like the three ranges of opinions, maybe
difference if it's biblical or rabbinic. So that's the framework. So we're
going to wrap that up right now and let's with one more
הלכה. halachah. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like
this. בעי
רב יוסף, ba'ei Rav Yosef, it is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
lines from the top, end of the line on ס"ו עמוד ב'.
Samech Vav Amud Bet. בעי רב יוסף ba'ei Rav Yosef asked, מי
גשמים שחישב עליהן להדיח את האיצטרובלין מהו. Mei geshamim shechishav aleihen lehadiach
et ha-itztroblin mahu. So here's the הלכה. halachah. We're talking about rainwater.
Now, when you have plants that are plants, fruit, or a grain
or whatever, it can only become טמא tamei after it's been picked
and after water has come in contact with it. And it's not
enough that water has come in contact with it, it has to
be that you actually actively put the water on it or in
a case let's say of rainwater the water spilled on it that
you wanted the water on it. All right, so that's the הלכה.
halachah. Now, and that only works on that desire for the water
to be on something only works if the water falls on something
that is not considered attached to the ground. Because of course think
about it, you got your plants growing, you always want it to
rain or not always but whatever, when it's supposed to rain you
want it to rain and you want the rain to fall on
it, right, then the הלכה halachah would be everything would become susceptible.
So it's only when both the thing itself is not attached and
you want the water on it and you wanted the water on
something that was not attached. So for example, let's say I here,
I'm very lazy and I don't do the dishes, and I hear
that it's going to rain, so I say oh perfect, so what
I'm going to do is bring my dishes out into the rain
and let the rain take care of wash my dishes. So here's
my dish and I bring it out into the rain and I
let the rain fall on it. Okay, and the rain falls on
it and washes my dish, okay, maybe I squirted a little soap
in it beforehand I don't know, anyway and after the rain falls
on my like mug here, it rolls off of my mug and
hits my apple that has been picked from the tree. So even
though I didn't want the apple, the rain to fall on the
apple, maybe I didn't care, maybe I for some reason I actively
didn't want it, doesn't matter, once I wanted the rain to fall
on something that was not attached to the ground, okay, then that
rain is considered like significant, okay, it's like attached to my desire,
and then when that rolls off and hits this apple, it makes
the apple susceptible to become טמא. tamei. So that's the basic הלכה.
halachah. All right, now here's the question we have. Let's say rather
than me wanting to wash my mug here, what I wanted was
I had my איצטרובלין. itztroblin. Everybody should have an איצטרובלין. itztroblin. Okay,
my איצטרובלין itztroblin if you remember is the frame that I have
that's attached to the ground that is for my, you know, is
for my like millstone, okay, so I think it's what it's for,
my millstone. I'm going to just check רשב"ם Rashbam what he says
about איצטרובלין. itztroblin. I think he says, yeah, for the millstone.
Okay, so I have,
I don't know where to draw it,
okay, I don't know, I assume it looks like something like this,
some type of a wooden frame. Okay, my millstone is here, okay,
and this wooden frame is attached to the ground. But it's like,
you know, it's not like a brick building, it's like a somewhat,
you know, independent
thing that a, well that's right I made it look like a
table, but you know I imagined that it's sort of like an
open-air type of a frame. Whatever, it's got, you know, these
wood beams that are, you know, that make an open frame as
it were and I somehow, you know, insert it and attach it
into the ground. So is that considered that's תלוש, tolush, first it
existed as a frame, ולבסוף חיברו, ulbesof chibro, and then I attached
it, right, like חקקו ולבסוף חיברו, chakako ulbesof chibro, I attached it.
Is the and now I hear it's about to rain and I
want the rain to fall on this to rinse it off. So
it's back to our old question. Is something that was existed as
a vessel and then was attached, is that considered a vessel and
is it considered detached and then when the rain hits it, it'll
be the water that makes the water like significant and then it
rolls onto the grain and it makes the grain susceptible to becoming
טמא? tamei? Or is this considered part of the ground and my
desire to rinse it off does not affect the status of the
rain and does not allow the rain to make the, you know,
to make the food susceptible for becoming טמא? tamei? All right, you
see, it's just like the questions we had before, except rather than
asking about a question of is it מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah or
what does it do to a מקוה mikvah or is it sold
together with the house, here it's applying this question of the status
of something that was detached and a vessel and is now attached
to the ground and asking what's its status for being an independent
vessel or not for this הלכה halacha about rain water. Now, the
question is, why is the גמרא Gemara asking this as if it
has special considerations? Why shouldn't it fall directly into all of the
debates that we said yesterday, right? Why does this deserve separate treatment?
So let's read the גמרא, Gemara, that's the question תוספות Tosafot asks
and we'll see what תוספות Tosafot says in the גמרא. Gemara. But
it's basically the same issue we had yesterday, applying it to this
or applying this new הלכה halacha to this question. What is this
status?
That's an interesting thing to do, is it?
Well, yes, if only if you want the rain to hit the
thing. You need that intent that you want the rain to wash
this thing. If you don't want the rain to wash it, it
has no status. But your intent doesn't change the status of whether
this is considered part of the ground or an independent object. Okay,
yes, Michael.
I was just thinking since רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is מטהר metaher
this תנור של עכנאי, tanur shel achnai, right? The same like thing?
Oh,
that's interesting. I hadn't thought about combining those. Because with חוליות chulyot
and, you know, like it's made...
Oh, that's interesting. I hadn't thought about combining those רבי אליעזר's. Rabbi
Eliezers. Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: מהו לזרעים? mahu l'zraim? What's the story if
it goes onto grain? Okay, so אליבא דרבי אליעזר, aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer,
according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer דאמר d'amar who says כל המחובר
לקרקע הרי הוא כקרקע, kol hamichubar l'karka harei hu k'karka,
anything even if it was a vessel now it's attached to the
ground, it's like a part of the ground, לא תיבעי לך, lo
tibaei lach, then it's obvious, this is a part of the ground.
כי תיבעי לך אליבא דרבנן ki tibaei lach aliba d'rabbanan according to
the
rabbis דאמרי אינו כקרקע d'amri eino k'karka
that they said by the shelf, if you made a shelf and
attached it to the wall or even if you first built a
shelf into the wall, you know, all these things, once it's a
vessel, it's its own status. So maybe what would be the story
here? Would that be, would this be independent or not? So the
גמרא Gemara says מאי תיקו, mai teiku, we don't know. Now the
question is, what do you mean you don't know? You just got
through saying that for the rabbis, once you, you know, even if
you've attached something, it remains its own status. Why should this be
different? So what תוספות Tosafot says is, is that there's a good
reason why this should be different. Because until now, right, and this
is actually relevant, I sort of mentioned the issue the other day,
if you remember, about things like a toilet. Okay, I mean I
mentioned it because it's a relevant הלכה. halacha. So if you say
the rabbis, well, it's a vessel, it's a toilet and now I
attach it to the ground, so it remains a vessel. Whoa, whoa,
wait. Something maybe that is made and its entire functionality and its
entire purpose of being made is for the sake of being attached
to the ground is a little different than like a shelf or
a pipe which can have functionality and can exist, you know, attached
to the ground or not attached to the ground. So that's what
תוספות Tosafot says basically is going on here. We know the רבנן
rabbanan say that something that's a vessel that's attached remains a vessel.
But what about something like an איצטרובלין itztroblin that really is made
fundamentally to be attached to the ground and to stay there and
it was never really made to exist independent of the ground? What
would be that status? Would it be considered part of the ground
or not? And the גמרא Gemara says תיקו. teiku. Yes.
Sorry, I just wasn't sure if you've covered it, but isn't it
like the same רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer similar conversation to the תנור
של עכנאי?
tanur shel achnai? Michael just said that two minutes ago. So the
two of you can get together
and do a nice sort of a presentation on that. But okay,
excellent. Okay, anyway, so if you take a look, let's. Yeah, they're
the same story about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן rabbanan
arguing about whether a certain oven was טמא tamei and טהור tahor
and he, whether it was pure or impure, and he said that
it was that it was pure, they said impure, and then he
said let's, you know, let the tree bend backward and let the
walls of the בית מדרש Beit Midrash bend in and a heavenly
voice come out. So anyway, the core of the debate was that
he was more prepared to say this thing was pure in the
same way here he's prepared, you know, his approach is more seeing
these things as part of the ground and as pure. That's רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, right. Okay, anyway, so תוספות Tosafot says like this,
תוספות Tosafot says, so let me, let me just read this to
you, it's a... Six lines, one, two, three, six lines from the
bottom in תוספות. Tosfos. He says the following, like five words in,
he says ובאיצטרוביאל דוקא מיבעי ליה. U'v'istrobiyol davka mibayei lei. The question
specifically is about this frame that maybe this frame is different than
like the shelf or the pipe. והכי קמיבעי ליה. V'hachi kamibayei lei.
Here's the question. איצטרובל דבטל לגבי קרקע לגבי מכר לרבנן. Istrobiyal dibatal
lgabei karka lgabei mecher l'rabbanan. אי דמכתשת. Ei dimachteshet. ייהוי בטל לגמרי
Yihavei batel l'gamre
כמו כותל kmo kotel
וחשוב נמי מחובר לעניין הכשר זרעים. v'chashiv nami mechubar l'inyan hechsher zraim.
Right.
So maybe he says like if you think about it right and
this is the point I made the other day. Everything pretty much
was detached and now attached. A house existed as stones that were
then attached to the ground. So you basically have a range, right?
Even the rabbis that say that the, this is how the debate
started, which was the what do you call it, the mortar that
was attached to the ground, that was the מכתשת. machteshet. The rabbis
say it's considered to be not attached and it's not sold with
the house. So תוספות Tosfos says you've got the following range. Here's
your mortar. Hold on.
Let me do this so I do not get messy marker on
myself. You can ignore that for now. This
is what happens to be
too active of a teacher.
So, okay. So here's this mortar, I don't even know exactly how
to make what to make a mortar look like. Okay, here's a
mortar that's attached to the ground. Okay, and the rabbis say that
that is not sold with the house. It's considered not to be
attached. Here's the actual wall. Okay, you got a wall that also
existed as stones and now is attached. Okay, and they say it
is sold, that is considered to be like the ground. Okay, you
know, or like whatever. And this is like this is considered to
be a כלי, kli, a vessel. All right, some things even though
they start unattached, you know, now they're totally made as building materials
to be attached, once they're attached they're part of the ground. Some
things are basically vessels that are just right now they're fixed into
the ground. Okay, and in the middle you've got this frame. Okay,
this frame is not like a big wall but on the other
hand its real purpose is to, you know, be planted in the
ground and to be a frame for this millstone. So the question
is which category does this fit into? Is this considered, you know,
sort of like I asked you about like a toilet, right? It's
fundamentally made to be in the ground. There's even the rabbis who
say something detached, there's something like a vessel that's attached is considered
a vessel, not everything is like an independent vessel. And which category
does this fit into? Is it like the wall or is it
like the vessel? And that's for, so one application is this question
about the rain and
about for the grain and then the rain falls on the grain.
Now, as far as our משנה's mishna concerned for whether it's sold
with the house or not sold with the house, right, our משנה
mishna says, now I have to remind myself, I think it says
it is sold with the house, right? What does our משנה mishna
say?
Our משנה mishna says yes, it is sold with the house. So
as far as whether it's sold, it's grouped with this. But that
the question is, you know, for there might be different considerations for
what you intended to sell and for objectively whether we view something
as attached to the ground or as a vessel. And that's our
question about this איצטרובל istrobiyal and that's what תוספות Tosfos says. Okay,
so he just read one more line of תוספות, Tosfos, he says
like this. אי בטל לגמרי כמו כותל. Ei batel l'gamre kmo kotel.
Is it like fully part of the ground like the wall? וחשוב
נמי מחובר לעניין הכשר זרעים. V'chashiv nami mechubar l'inyan hechsher zraim. And
that would apply for other laws like this issue of the rain.
או דילמא לעניין הכשר זרעים לא חשיב מחובר כמו כותל. O dilma
l'inyan hechsher zraim lo chashiv mechubar kmo kotel. Or no, maybe it's
really considered like not part of the ground and it's really in
other הלכות halachos considered like a vessel. ומיהו אלא דוקא
לעניין מכר משום עין יפה. U'mihu ella davka l'inyan mecher mishum ayin
yafa. And only by sales do we say, yeah, you're selling your
house, you'll sell these things as well even if they're technically not
considered part of the ground. Okay, so this is again just showing
that there's a continuum, it's not all black and white. There are
definitely some things that were separate and then they're now they're part
of the ground. There are definitely some things that even when they're
attached according to the רבנן rabbanan are conceptually still attached vessels but
still vessels. And then there's something that's in a middle category. This
is overlapping.
In other words, עין יפה ayin yafa would extend to things that
are או דאורייתא o
d'oraisa aren't a part of it. Right, that's why מכר mecher is
always different, because מכר mecher could be things that are מטלטלין metaltelin
and עין יפה ayin yafa will bring them in. Or you could
do the opposite. עין רעה Ayin ra'ah could say things that are
technically part of ground in other areas but for מכר mecher we
take them out. So that's why מכר mecher really is not a
determinant factor for anything else because that really more goes by, you
know, people's general intention and so on.
So one criteria is עין יפה ayin yafa would tend to include
things that are more like the ground.
Yes,
right, obviously because it's in this gray area that gets swept in,
but in other areas it would be considered on the other side
of the line. Okay, let's, so that's the question. Now let's wrap
this up. שלח ליה רב נחמיה בריה דרב יוסף לרבה בריה דרב
הונא זוטי. Shlach lei Rav Nechemia brei d'Rav Yosef l'Rabbah brei d'Rav
Huna zuti. שלח ליה רב נחמיה בריה דרב יוסף לרבה בריה דרב
הונא זוטי Shlach lei Rav Nechemiah brei d'Rav Yosef l'Rabba brei d'Rav
Huna Zuti לנהרדעא. l'Neharde'a. So Rav Nechemiah the son of Rav Yosef
sent to Rabba the son of Rav Huna, the small one, the
minor one, לנהרדעא. l'Neharde'a. He sent, no, he sent him to go
to Neharde'a. כי אתיא Ki asya הא איתתא לקמך ha itesa lekamecha
and he said to him: I'm sending you to Neharde'a, when the
following woman comes to you, okay, and she's got because I know
there's a woman there that's trying to collect some property from the
estate, okay, and what was she trying to collect from her father's
estate, her father had passed away? אגביה עישור נכסי, Agbei issur nichsei,
collect her tenth of the property. What does the tenth of the
property mean? When a father marries off his daughters, he would normally
give them a significant dowry from the estate.
If he were to die, we assume that even though the daughters
don't get an inheritance in the estate, but by the way I
should say that what gets written into the כתובה, kesubah, part of
the standard כתובה kesubah document is something called כתובת חצי זכר, kesubas
chatzi zachar, half of a male,
which is, Bobby, it's a lot better than nothing, okay, in the
case that they would standard write in that the daughters would get
half portions of the estate. Okay, without that, according you know they
would get nothing, but the standard became to actually give them half
portions. What? Yeah, I know it's like a standard, not everything that's
a standard תנאי כתובה tnai kesubah is explicitly written in. Anyway, that's
beside, that's one thing, that's just what they would inherit, but let's
say there's a different consideration, which is what is their dowry if
they're unmarried? So if the father was alive, he would have given
them some significant dowry. Now he's not alive and there's this estate
that the brothers have inherited, is she not to is she going
to not get a dowry? So the הלכה halacha is that basically
the בית דין beis din would try
to look at how the father's
general sort of behavior and what if there were other daughters, what
did he give his other daughters, and try to assess and estimate
what he would have given her. If you don't have a good
way of assessing that, the default is she gets to take one
tenth of the value of the estate for her dowry. So think
about it, by the way, somebody's got a lot of kids, she
could wind up getting more than her brothers in terms of the
dowry. Okay, but again, maybe that's counterbalanced by the assessment of what
the father likely would have given. Anyway, that's עישור נכסי issur nichsei
that she gets after the father died, that she by like as
a rule of thumb if she's not married and is getting married
takes one tenth of the estate, עישור נכסי. issur nichsei. Now, she
could only take it, the general rule is like anybody that is
coming to collect from the estate, even the wife who is coming
to collect her כתובה kesubah from her dead husband's estate, only gets
it from landed property, from קרקע, karka, because the heirs are considered
to be like a not a direct continuation of the father, they're
instead like there's a whole question of exactly the status of the
heirs, but to some degree they're like somebody bought the property from
the father. So if you think about it, the wife and the
daughters have liens against the father husband's estate, he owed them this
כתובה kesubah money, right, or he will owe them money when he
dies, they have liens on the estate and now the estate passes
into the hands of the heirs. So they can collect, the wife
can collect her כתובה kesubah and the daughters can collect their dowry
from the landed property, but not from the מטלטלין, metaltelin, not from
like the cash, because they don't have liens
on looking at the cash value too.
Oh, that's an interesting question, yeah, that's a very good point.
Like Warren Buffett?
Right, right, right, you might be right. Yeah, yeah, he said, let's
say this guy has a million dollars in his bank accounts and
a hundred thousand dollars in land, so you want to throw out
over nine hundred thousand in bank accounts and a hundred thousand in
land, so you would say well, his entire wealth is a million
dollars, ten percent is a hundred thousand, so now she can collect
all of the land. Right, I believe that that is correct, that
you don't to assess the tenth, it's not a tenth of the
land, it's a tenth of the estate collectible from the land. Right.
So now the question was, it was so this woman is going
to come to you and I'm sending you maybe as an emissary
of בית דין, beis din, I want you to hear her case,
and she's going to want to collect her tenth of her estate
of the estate for her dowry from the dead father from from
her her dead father's estate. So can you so אגביה עישור נכסי
agbei issur nichsei go ahead, take care of her case, collect her
collect her tenth, אפילו מאיצטרובלא דריחיא. afilu me'itztrobla d'reichaya. And you should
collect it from any land you can find even from the איצטרובלא.
itztrobla. So I don't know how much the איצטרובלא itztrobla is worth,
this guy's estate might have been worth for all we know a
hundred dollars, so maybe she's getting only ten dollars, okay, you know,
poor people also had daughters and had dowries, but they were just
much smaller dowries. Okay, so so meaning like so obviously it's relevant
for us because this is showing that for purposes of at least
liens we're going to consider this to be part of the land,
okay, which is again sort of siding with the רבנן rabbanan against
I'm sorry, excuse me, siding with רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, thank you,
siding with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer against the רבנן rabbanan that we
will that seeing something that was attached detached and now attached.
as part of the ground. Now again, it's in a middle case,
not clear we would apply it to this case, right? But at
least in this middle case, seeing this as part of the ground.
Okay. אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi said רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
כי הוינן בי רב כהנא ki avinan be Rav Kahana when I
was in the house of רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, מגבי אפילו מאפידנא
דבתי magbi afilu me'apidna de'basi he would collect this tenth of the
estate for the for the dowry, even from the שכר בתים schar
batim from the from the rental profit of the homes. Okay, now
meaning that the father owned some rental properties and the father died
and now the rent is due and all of the tenants are
paying, you know, whatever, all their rent at the end of this
month. He would say, oh, that is profit coming from land, so
therefore that can go to the daughter to pay for her tenth
of her dowry, for her tenth of the estate.
Now תוספות Tosfos says wait, wait, I'm sorry.
He would get, take the actual rented property?
Right. ראובן שמעון ולוי Reuven, Shimon, and Levi inherited their father's estate.
He owns this nice high-rise building, this rental property, okay, and then
and it's rented out to, you know, I don't know, to מרדכי
ירמיהו וישעיהו, Mordechai, Yirmiyahu, and Yeshayahu, okay. So comes comes the end
of the month and they all pay their rent and now the
בית דין beis din says great, we're taking that rent and that's
giving that to דינה, Dinah, your sister, for her tenth of the
estate. And the חידוש chidush is that דינה Dinah only has a
right to landed property. This is cash. But it's cash that comes
from landed property. Now תוספות Tosfos wants to know, he says, when
exactly did this happen? Like after the the rent has been paid
and the cash is now sitting in the bank, so it's not
landed property, right? At that stage, you know, you don't you know,
is that you don't have a lien on that. If דינה Dinah
comes to the בית דין beis din before the rent is being
paid, well, then of course, the same way דינה Dinah could demand
to actually take a piece of the land itself, I'm possessing the
land and I'm selling the land, of course she has the right
to say, I'm going to take the land and benefit from its
rental value. So תוספות Tosfos says well, here's the case. The case
is that דינה Dinah came in the middle of the month, okay,
and the rent is due at the end of the month. So
right now it's the middle of the month. You might think she's
only entitled to rent that accrues from this point on, right? So
are you guys with me? Meaning the rent that was owed for
the first half of the month, well, then she hasn't yet exercised
her ownership over the land, it's only now she's coming to בית
דין. beis din. So maybe only now that she's coming to בית
דין beis din and she could take possession of the land is
she entitled to the rent from this point on but not from
the beginning of the month. And the חידוש chidush is אין שכירות
משתלמת אלא לבסוף ein sechirut mishtalemet ela le'basof
that since the rent is only due at the end of the
month,
then when she shows up in the middle of the month, then
she has now right to the full month's rent. Okay, so that's
how תוספות Tosfos explains what the חידוש chidush here is. Yes.
So if we go back to the example
before, a man say he has $100,000 worth of property, he has
$900,000 in the account. Let's say that $900,000 came from property he
had sold just before he died.
Right, so that's what תוספות Tosfos just discussed here.
Is that what we're talking about?
Yes, so that's what תוספות Tosfos discussed here. If she only her
rights only, well, it would be determined based on really I actually
think I misspoke before. I said it's determined like when she comes
to בית דין, beis din, but really well, actually, no, because I
think the debt is incurred. It's a good question. I have to
figure out when is the debt incurred? Is it when she like
gets engaged and at that time she's entitled or whatever אירוסין erusin
and whatever, she's entitled to her dowry? Is it, you know, is
it at the moment the father dies because eventually she'll be entitled
to her dowry? We
have to figure out like what is that critical point in time
where you define what is the thing that she has a lien
on? I think it most logically would be the moment the father
dies. What was land at that time and what was not land?
Let me just see if תוספות Tosfos discusses one minute.
Yeah, it's I'd have to check. That's a very good question. Like
what is the key moment, you know, that you determine when her
liens, which property her liens are on? I think it would go
by what was because the whole point, yeah, the whole point here
is that the liens only survive the father's death because they stay
on the property and they transfer with the property. So I think
it would have I'll double-check, but I'm pretty positive that it would
be based on what was property and what was cash, you know,
non-property, you know, non-real estate at the time of the father's death.
Presumably, a daughter can be seven years old when her father
dies and then 15 years later, exactly, exactly, yes.
stand this. I mean like this land that has an income producing
is very different than you know the land that just has a
house that isn't income producing. Right. She's entitled to get whatever it
I mean if she. Are you looking at the land value? Like,
you know, how much is this piece of dirt worth, or how
much is the income stream from the dirt?
Well obviously that determines its worth. If I own a piece of
land that's got a high rise building and we also own the
building or whatever, then a one percent ownership, whatever, that's all part
of the value of it.
But do they specifically look at the expected future value
of the income stream
over the course of like however long it goes?
I don't know, how much is the market value? The market value
incorporates all of that. Yeah, of course.
But it's so not considered מטלטלין? metaltelin? Correct.
Because the value, if the land is worth a lot because it's
got oil underneath it, or if it's worth a lot because it's
in Midtown Manhattan and it's got an apartment building built on it,
that just increases the value of the land. That's all, but that's
all the value of קרקע. karka.
And can she get to pick whichever it is, whichever part she
takes?
No, that's a different story. Somebody comes to collect with a lien,
you know, it's the person, it's the debtor that gets to sort
of choose. I mean it depends, actually, that's the whole, that's actually
the פרק Perek in גיטין Gittin about כתובת אישה. Kesubas Isha. Is
it נגבית מן הבינונית מן הזיבורית, nigves min habeinonis min haziboris, like
there's different classes of land. Okay, so you know, but so there's
some structure to how he gets to choose.
But there's a reason for her to get this, right, from this
whatever it is, this עמלא? amla?
Yeah, well the point was that
according to תוספות, Tosafos, the חידוש chiddush was that she is able
to, there wouldn't have been enough maybe to just whatever, but she
can collect already from the beginning of the month. Yes.
In that example about $100 and then ninety percent in cash. Yeah.
So why is the cash, what's the category of the cash? It's
מטלטלין? metaltelin?
Yes, cash is מטלטלין. metaltelin.
Okay, so she wouldn't, they wouldn't get that, right?
Right. But my עיקר ikar is correct that it would go into
the determination of the value of the estate, but it would be
for inheritance
and for her to figuring out her ten percent. But the lien
would only be on the landed part of the estate, from the
land. But the amount that she would get would be determined by
the whole estate. Right. Okay. But the question about like when you
determine the land
versus מטלטלין metaltelin split, you know,
whether, presumably it's the moment of death of the father, but I'd
have to check that. Okay. Let's, by the way, look at the
last רשב"ם Rashbam to wrap up this case, before the lines get
wide. Two lines before the lines get wide, he said, עד דלא
מצטרובלי דהינו מטלטלי קבועין בקרקע שמע מינה דסוגיא דשמעתא כרבי אליעזר סבירא
ליה. ad dlo mitztrubli dehinu metalteli kevuyin bekarka shema mina desugya deshamata
k'Rabbi Eliezer savira leh. There you go, Bobby. It sounds like the
end of the discussion is that we consider this איצטרובלי itztrobli to
be part of the ground, like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דסבר כל
המחובר לקרקע הרי הוא כקרקע. desavar kol hamachubar lekarka harey hu kekarka.
כן פירש רבינו חננאל והכי פסק אליבא דהלכתא וכן עיקר. Ken peirash
Rabbeinu Chananel vehachi pasak aliba dehilchasa vechein ikar. So that sounds like
a straight פסק psak like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, even in like
this case. Right? So that's the question. But תוספות Tosafos has pointed
out that this is a middle case. So this becomes very relevant,
and again, I know it sounds like this is all very obscure,
but it has very relevant for מקווה mikvah הלכות, halachos, for נדה
niddah הלכות, halachos, whatever, whether you consider this considered מטלטלין metaltelin or
קרקע karka actually. Did you talk about נדה? niddah? I think you
left by then. Well, the whole idea that if a stain is
found on something that is מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah versus not מקבל
טומאה. mekabel tumah. So anyway, so we פסקן, pasken, this is like
קרקע. karka. It sounds like the רשב"ם Rashbam we pretty much would
פסקן pasken everything would be like קרקע, karka, but תוספות Tosafos says
this is a middle case, so it's at least for תוספות Tosafos
that we're.
Okay, let's move on now to the next משנה. Mishnah. I appreciate
that everybody really enjoyed that, and maybe you're trying to make us
not get too far ahead, but let's go now to the next
משנה. Mishnah. המוכר את החצר. Hamocher es hachatzer.
Somebody who sells now, you're not selling the house, now you're actually
selling the courtyard. Okay. It could be your individual yard in front
of your house. Most likely what this was would be a series
of multiple houses that had a shared courtyard. Okay. So המוכר את
החצר. Hamocher es hachatzer. It's like imagine nowadays, we have a court,
except instead of a court where we have front yards and then
we have a court which is just where the cars drive, imagine
you don't have individual front yards, you have all the houses and
then a shared courtyard that they all equally share. And I'm selling,
you know, I'm selling to Michal my entire... I own this entire
courtyard, okay, with the homes. And we write in the document, I'm
selling you the חצר. chatzer. Now what does that mean? Does it
mean just the yard, or does it mean also with the houses
in the yard? So the משנה Mishnah says מכר בתים בורות שיחין
ומערות. machar batim boros shichin ume'aros. You sell everything. You sell the
houses that are attached to the yard, you tell
the wells, the cisterns, all these various things, even though when you
sell the house you don't sell the well, that's because a well
and a house are separate structures. But this yard, the implication is
the yard with all of the structures that are in the yard.
So there are houses, there are wells, there are cisterns, all of
that gets sold. אבל לא את המטלטלין. Aval lo es hametaltelin. But
you still do not sell the things that are not connected to
the ground. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says even the things we mentioned
in the previous משנה, Mishnah, like this, for example, this מכתשת machteshes
here, right, you know, even things like that, you know, different like
even things that are normally used with the house, like all of
the furniture in the homes, you know, and all of... whatever that
type of stuff, it doesn't matter. You're only selling the stuff that's
part of the ground. Okay, בזמן שאמר לו היא וכל מה שבתוכה,
Bizman she'amar lo hi vechol mah she-betochah, if I say I'm selling
you it with all of its contents, הרי כולם מכורין, harei kulam
mechorin, everything is sold, and this everything, as it according to later
becomes clear, really means everything. It means the furnishings,
it means like if I left some, I don't know, my bike
in the apartment,
any type of stuff, even stuff that you would say is maybe
personal items, my dishes, okay, all of that stuff, because now that
you're saying the courtyard and not just an individual home, it's seen
as being a bigger sale. Now, logically, that doesn't make as much
sense, right? Because you would think if I'm focused on this particular
house and I say all of the contents, you're thinking more about
the contents of a house,
and to me that might be
more inclusive of the full contents. If you say the courtyard and
all of its contents, you might say, oh come on, when we're
talking about a whole courtyard, obviously I mean that the individual people
can take their individual items out of the homes. But we don't
say that. We say when the sale is bigger and you say
all of the contents, then we're including, it's more inclusive. So whereas
when you said all of the contents of the home, if you
remember the discussion the other day, it said that was not fully
inclusive. It would not include things that normally people would lend out,
that normally would not
stay permanent within the house. It wouldn't include my wallet and my
bike and my dishes and my probably would include my refrigerator and
my stove, okay, but it wouldn't include things that I would normally
take out of the house. Here when you say all the contents,
it really is all the contents. The one exception that we're going
to find out is it doesn't include the food, but includes all
the objects that are in the homes. Yes.
But if the homes are being rented out to other people... Right.
Right. You can't sell things you don't own. That is correct, and
that might be part of the balance here, right? Like I probably
don't live in ten houses. So if I own all ten houses,
they're probably rentals. So probably the only thing I can sell is
any of my objects that are in the home. That is correct.
Yes.
Along those lines, what is the situation that you
owned this like or whatever?
Right, that there are multiple owners and a classic case would be
that you had separate owners of the homes and then shared ownership
of the courtyard. But the גמרא Gemara has cases where people own
entire towns, so it sounds like it could be I own the
courtyard and I'm renting out the properties. All right, so,
okay. So, but yes, obviously it would only be the stuff that...
so that's right, that creates some type of a balance. Like if
that it's not what the renters have in the house, it's what
I own in the house.
But if the renter's bike is sitting in the yard, that's still
not...
Obviously, right, I can't sell something I don't own. Correct. בין כך
ובין כך, Bein kach uvein kach, even if I say I'm selling
everything, לא מכר לא את המרחץ ולא את בית הבד שבתוכה. lo
machar lo et hamerchatz velo et beit habad she-betochah. You do not
sell if there is a like a separate enterprise, not just a
separate unit like a cistern, okay, it's a separate structure, it's not
a home, but you said everything, all the structures. But something like
a bathhouse or an olive press, those are things which are considered
to be like separate enterprises. They're not connected to the living of
a
courtyard. It's all the things that are connected to living in a
place. So living in a place is you've got the yards and
you've got the water and you've got the well and you've got
those things, right? But the idea that you've got a business enterprise
here or that you're whether you're renting it out to others or
whether for you're just sort of pressing your own olives, that's not
part of the normal functions of a courtyard. So that is considered
to be independent. Okay, that's not included. רבי אליעזר אומר המוכר את
החצר לא מכר אלא אוירה של חצר. Rabbi Eliezer omer hamocher et
hachatzar lo machar ela avirah shel chatzar. He says, nope, if you
sell I'm selling you the courtyard, you're only selling the air of
the courtyard. Now the רשב"ם Rashbam says it doesn't literally mean the
air, it means the ground, but you're only selling the yard. You're
not selling the homes. Okay? So that's what a חצר chatzar is,
it's a yard, you didn't sell the homes. Now of course the
big question that everybody wants to know is why don't we look
at the price and let the price help tell us whether you
meant the yard or the yard with the homes? And this is
the question of הדמים מודיעים. hadamim modiin. Can you use the price
to determine how to interpret these terms in the document? And often
when it comes to land, we don't say that. And the reason
תוספות Tosafot says is because there's a lot of wide range of
pricing for land. Like people can pay a lot for land because
they're speculators or whatever they might be, and therefore you cannot really
say that you can go by the price. Okay, it's still funny
that you don't even factor it in at all, okay, but anyway,
but I guess what the point is that if this is why
you need to hire a lawyer, right? If everybody understands the rules
going in, if it's very clear the term חצר chatzar means X,
the term this means that, right? So and you want law to
be clear, you don't want to have to debate every single time
it says חצר, chatzar, let's go figure out and have to clog
up the courts with trying to determine all the... stances and based
on this price or whatever, you want there to be clear rules.
So, it’s not unfair as long as everybody knows what the rules
are, you know? So, anyways, that’s why we’re not really going to
go by דמי מודעים, damei modim, we’re going to make it, we’re
going to just have clear positions. It’s debated, okay, but, you know,
but each one of them takes a clear position.
Yes, in previous cases where we’re talking about where everybody had a
home in the courtyard had a mutual ownership of the courtyard?
Yes, that’s what Micha was asking. Yes, but this is a case
where one person owns the courtyard with the homes, owns everything. And
he’s renting it all out. And now he’s selling the underlying property
to somebody else.
But
Rabbi Eliezer is conceiving it as if he didn’t own the homes,
right?
No, he owns it, he just didn’t sell it. I own the
whole thing, and I sell you- I’m selling you my חצר. chatzer.
Okay, does my חצר chatzer mean just the yard or does it
mean all the homes in the yard?
What’s the practical
bottom line here then about all the people who are living in
these homes and this guy is selling the courtyard to somebody? Right.
Well, if- I presumably their rental of the home includes a rental
of the courtyard, so, you know, I mean, that’s always a question.
You sell the underlying property, what does it do to somebody’s lease,
you know? Alright, let’s take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan המוכר את החצר hamocher et hachatzer מכר בתים
החיצוניים ובתים הפנימיים. machar batim hachitzoniyim ubatim hapnimiyim. Now you remember the
good old front house and back house, right? So
you’ve got your courtyard here, right, and you’ve got your homes, and
they open straight into the courtyard. But then there are some homes
that don’t open straight into the courtyard. They’re back room- you know,
back rooms to the main home, right? So you might say, well,
if I’m selling you the courtyard, I’m selling you the homes that
are directly open in. But this thing, which is not directly attached
to the courtyard, right, that maybe I’m not selling. But the bottom
line is no, it’s not like this has an exit to a
different street, you know, it’s not directly attached, but the way this
guy gets out is by going through here and going through the
courtyard. So those homes are sold as well.
Okay, ובית החולסאות. uveit hacholsaot. Now the רשב"ם Rashbam says that the
word חולסאות cholsaot comes from the word חול chol and that means
like a patch of white sand that maybe you had in the
courtyard, which you might think- which they would use that sand for
like making glass, and you might think that, you know, that’s not-
it’s maybe that’s sort of like the מרחץ, merchatz, maybe that’s sort
of like the בית הבד, beit habad, you know, maybe that’s not
the type of thing that’s not normal just living space, maybe that’s
more like a income type of a thing. You can like take
that sand and sell it, you know, for making of, you know,
for making glass or whatever. But the answer is, I mean, that’s
a good argument if that’s what it is, but somehow the answer
is like no, it’s still just ground and therefore it’s included. Okay,
that’s the way he explains it. I don’t know, what does- I
didn’t get a chance- what does his name say? Well, they quote
the רשב"ם, Rashbam, but
what's-his-name there, שטיינזלץ, Steinsaltz, does he have- בבא, Bava, does he have
a different explanation?
Steinsaltz commentary said a version of the text in which sand fields
are not included in the sale.
Ah, not included. But he still interprets it to be sand fields
like the רשב"ם. Rashbam. He doesn’t give a different meaning to that
term.
המאירי, Hameiri, רבינו
גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, רשב"ם, Rashbam, many commentaries explain the term as referring
to a place containing high-quality sand from which, as you said, glass
is produced. Right, okay.
And he doesn’t give another explanation for it.
Yet others explain that it means a building built of stones from
which the glass is produced, making it an exceptional building on- in
its own right, yet nevertheless it’s considered part of the courtyard. Yet
others argue that courtyards do not normally contain such a building, and
therefore they interpret the term as referring to a building without floorboards
where the floor is comprised of sand. Such a building is generally
not used for dwelling, but for storage.
Ah, that’s interesting.
Okay. Others proposed that this refers to a rocky area- sorry.
Okay, no, it's okay. Okay, so there are a lot of different
interpretations. But what is interesting that I didn’t know is that some
have the גירסא girsa that it’s not sold. Because, you know, once
you actually say that, it’s interesting, right? If like- if like an
olive press isn’t sold and a bathhouse isn’t sold, because those are
separate enterprises, that’s not just like domicile, it’s not just living space,
then you might say, well, a sand field, that’s about selling the
sand, and people like- it’s not like kids play in it, it’s
not like a sandbox, right? It’s presumably it was used for sale,
then there’d be a good argument to say it would not be
sold. So it’s interesting that some of the versions say it was
not sold. Okay, that’s the ובית החולסאות. veit hacholsaot. חנויות פתוחות לתוכה.
chanuyot petuchot letocha. Now how about
the
stores that are- you have- you have stores. Okay, now here that’s
like a really interesting middle case between the stores- right, what is
it? There’s three things: it’s residential, commercial, and industrial, right? So, well,
anyway, but okay, but the point is it’s a different type of
commercial. Right, so the wine press, or the olive press, is a
type of
a- it’s like a separate enterprise that’s not, you know, that’s sort
of like- you just happen to be situated in this courtyard, but
it’s basically an enterprise that’s like available to
everybody, right? So
you’re just- servicing the courtyard. It's providing like the fruits and the
vegetables or whatever. It's like a store that is help, giving the
the basic, you know, staples to the people in the courtyard, right?
You got a little... so there you could say, that's not just
סתם stam an enterprise that happens to be here. That's like part
of this residential space is that we have a little store here.
You know, so how do you conceptualize that? So it says, it
depends. חנויות פתוחות לתוכה נמכרות עמה Chanuyot p'tuchot l'tocha nimcharot immah
If the storefront opens into the courtyard, then it's part of the
courtyard. ושאין פתוחות לתוכה v'she'ein p'tuchot l'tocha if it's not open into
it, if it's if it's here but the the door is, you
know, the storefront is here and people from outside the courtyard come
into it, then it just happens to be there and it's not
sold with it. ושאין פתוחה לתוכה אינה נמכרת עמה v'she'ein p'tucha l'tocha
einah nimcheret immah פתוחה לכאן ולכאן p'tucha l'chan ul'chan Now let's say
it has two storefronts. You open it here, so you get the
courtyard business, and you open it here, so you get the street
business. Okay, so do you conceptualize it as part of the courtyard
or not? So it says נמכרות עמה nimcharot immah that is part
of the courtyard.
רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer now we're going to see an
opposing opinion in a minute. רבי אליעזר אומר המוכר את החצר לא
מכר אלא מילוסא Rabbi Eliezer omer hamocher et hachatzer lo machar ela
milusa If you sell the חצר chatzer you're only selling the... again,
another word that basically means the space, but you're not actually selling
the house. של חצר shel chatzer אמר מר פתוחה לכאן ולכאן נמכרת
עמה Amar mar p'tucha l'chan ul'chan nimcheret immah
If it's open at both ends, it is part of the courtyard
sold with it. והתני רבי חייא V'hatani Rabbi Chiya Rabbi Chiya teaches,
אינה נמכרת עמה einah nimcheret immah
that no, if it's open at both ends it basically is not
part of the courtyard and it's not sold with it. So mar
says, לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult. הא דרוב תשמישתיה לגו
הא דרוב תשמישתיה לבר ha d'rov tashmishtayh l'gav ha d'rov tashmishtayh l'var
Where is its basic business? If basically it does business with the
courtyard, but it's got a little side opening, you know, to do
a little business with outside people, then it's part of the courtyard.
If its basic storefront is facing out and it gets, you know,
but to make things convenient for people in the courtyard, he's got
a little opening there too and does a little amount of business
with people in the courtyard, then it's not part of the courtyard.
So this is a more gray case and you have to assess
the situation. Okay, presumably again we're talking about that somebody has rented
that business and the question is whether the underlying property is being
sold or not. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר המוכר את החצר לא מכר
אלא דירתה של חצר Rabbi Eliezer omer hamocher et hachatzer lo machar
ela dirata shel chatzer Okay, you're not selling the houses, you're just
selling the space.
אמר רבא אי דאמר ליה דירתא Amar Rava ei d'amar leih dirata
then it depends what term you used. Okay, if you said דירתא
dirata דירתא dirata means like domicile. Okay, and if that was the
word you used for the חצר chatzer because we're going to see
in a minute that the Aramaic word for the חצר chatzer is
דרתא darta דלת ריש תיו אלף dalet reish tav aleph דירתא dirata
or
דרתא darta דירתא dirata
דירה dira means a domicile. So if you used a word for
the courtyard which emphasized, I'm trying to think of an English equivalent,
but you know, different words have different connotations. So if you used
a word, it means courtyard, but like the heavy etymology and emphasis
of the word has this like echo of this sense of domicile,
דירתא dirata then it means you're thinking of the courtyard as the
place where everybody is living and as a place, you know, and
a place with
homes, residences, and therefore it obviously means with the residences. Okay, I
mean, if you want to think about it maybe one way of
thinking differently is like if you said yard, or did you say
courtyard? Right? When you say yard, you just mean the yard. When
you say courtyard, you're sort of thinking about the homes together with
the courtyard, you know, so I can't think of an exact English
parallel. But that's what רבא Rava is saying. אי דאמר ליה דירתא
דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דבתי משמע ei d'amar leih dirata d'chulei alma
lo pligi d'batei mashma Then there wouldn't be a debate between רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma דבתי משמע d'batei
mashma it obviously means the yard with the homes. כי פליגי דאמר
ליה דרתא ki pligi d'amar leih darta not דירתא dirata but דרתא
darta but still obviously has the same four letters to it. מר
סבר תרביצא משמע mar savar tarbitza mashma that just means the
yard, ומר סבר בתי משמע umar savar batei mashma No, this word
still has דירה dira in it and that still suggests the homes
with the yard. איכא דאמרי ika d'amri some say, אמר רבא amar
Rava that Rava says, אי דאמר ליה דרתא ei d'amar leih darta
no, actually if you even if you said דרתא darta and not
דירתא dirata כולי עלמא לא פליגי דבתי משמע chulei alma lo pligi
d'batei mashma That's the Aramaic word for חצר chatzer but still it's
a word that has echoes of דירה dira and therefore it means
with the homes. Okay, and therefore everybody, even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
would agree it means with the houses. כי פליגי דאמר ליה חצר
ki pligi d'amar leih chatzer You used the Hebrew word. Because the
word חצר chatzer has no echo of any word that means home,
right? So there we can more debate. Okay, מר סבר חצר אוירא
משמע mar savar chatzer avira mashma it just means the yard, the
space, ומר סבר כחצר המשכן umar savar k'chatzer hamishkan No, it's like
the חצר המשכן chatzer hamishkan of the Torah, which calls it החצר
hachatzer right?
You always used... the משכן, mishkan, right, and here was your קודש
קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, right, whatever, you know, here's your כלים, keilim, okay,
your פרוכת, parochet, anyway, and then he calls this whole thing the
חצר, chatzer, right? So this is the חצר, chatzer, but the חצר
chatzer includes the משכן mishkan itself, which is God's house. So once
again by the way, notice how much we constantly are referring to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the משכן Mishkan in talking about
homes, okay? So once again, your God's home here, the חצר chatzer
included the house. All right, so.
And here they call it airspace.
Airspace, right. But you but presumably I mean again I assume you
don't you know the reason I said the yard itself is and
the רשב"ם Rashbam seems to say this is that I can't imagine
that you're just selling air rights and you don't actually own the
ground itself. I assume it means the the you know the the
רשב"ם Rashbam sounds like it actually means you do own the yard
you just don't own the homes you don't own the land that
the homes are built on. The space in the sense of like
that space between the homes, but it actually is the yard itself,
I mean at least that's what the רשב"ם Rashbam says.
So it's the airspace that is the open space of the courtyard.
The open space of the courtyard, right, but obviously it means the
ground, right. Okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, ואמר רבא אמר רב נחמן מכר לו חולסיס ומצולה. ve-amar
Rava amar Rav Nachman machar lo chulsis u-metzula. Now we're going to
deal with a different הלכה. halakha. Not a question of what you
included, but we've had this question before. When you do an act
of חזקה chazaka on one plot of land, does it work on
another plot of land? Now I want to remind you of what
we discussed before. You might remember this one when we were discussing
about a case about a גר ger who died and if you
do a חזקה chazaka on one piece of his property, does it
work on another piece of his property? And the basic point was
like this. In the case of a גר ger who died, since
there is no party who is selling it who is, you know,
דעת אחרת מקנה, daas acheres makneh, who's intending to sort of pull
it all together, it's just a question of what your physical act
signifies. There we say that if it's not seen as one plot
of land, if it's two plots, a חזקה chazaka on one part,
like remember the חזקה chazaka of like ניכוש ודרוך, nichush and derech,
right? Digging a hole, making a fence, whatever it is, that works
only on that one plot and not on something which is defined
as a separate plot. And then the question is how do you
define a separate plot? But if I am selling you the land
and I am intending to sell you two pieces and some throw
in especially if you've paid me the money for both plots, that
pulls them all together in one package and you can do a
חזקה chazaka on one and it works for the other. You can
even do a חזקה chazaka on a piece of land in New
York and it also works and I'm selling you that plus a
property in Miami, it works for both. Okay, so with that in
mind, let's see what this is going what this this is going
to talk about. Okay. So אמר רבא אמר רב נחמן מכר לו
חולסיס, Amar Rava amar Rav Nachman machar lo chulsis, if I'm selling
you this like this
sand plot, ומצולה, u-metzula, and I'm also selling you a pond. Okay.
And apparently I'm selling you the like also the, you know, actual
underlying like whatever, you know, dirt or the underlying ground of the
pond. Now what do you want a pond for? So the רשב"ם
Rashbam has two possibilities. One is you want to go fishing in
it and you want to sort of that, and the other is
maybe you actually want to go mining in it and you think
there might be some gold underneath the ground because you're obviously not
going to be like walking in it or, you know, making a
house in it. Okay, but those are two very different functions, maybe
they're even two different types of, you know,
economic enterprises. One is making sand, the other is I don't know
mining or selling fish or whatever. Okay, so so those are these
very two distinct types of properties. Okay, so החזיק בחולסיס לא קנה
מצולה החזיק במצולה לא קנה חולסיס. Hechizik be-chulsis lo kanah metzula hechizik
be-metzula lo kanah chulsis.
If you do a חזקה chazaka in one, it does not you're
trying to buy both but you'd have to do separate acts of
חזקה. chazaka. חזקה chazaka on one piece doesn't work on the other,
even with somebody intending to sell you both and their intent to
package them together. So the גמרא Gemara questions this. So the גמרא
Gemara says: איני? Eini? Is that really true? ואמר שמואל מכר לו
עשר שדות בעשר מדינות, ve-amar Shmuel machar lo eser sadot be-eser medinot,
if you want to sell ten different fields in ten different, you
know, states, כיון שהחזיק באחת מהן קנה כולם. keivan she-hechizik be-achat me-hen
kanah kulum. One חזקה chazaka works for all if there's somebody intending
to sell you them all together, especially if you're also even have
already paid for all them together, the רשב"ם Rashbam throws that in,
then certainly it packages them all, so why should this be any
different? The גמרא Gemara says: No, התם הוא דסדנא דארעא חד הוא.
hatam hu desadna de-ara chad hu. There's because like the sort of
the plot of land, you know, the is all one, like all
the continents are connected, okay, וכולו חד
הוא וכולו חד תשמישא, ve-kulu chad hu ve-kulu chad tashmisha, and they
share a common use. If I'm selling you all these plots and
they're all basically, you know, I don't know, like wheat fields. Now
of course the question is you know how what defines common use,
but let's go on. אבל הכא האי תשמישא לחווד והאי תשמישא לחווד.
Aval hacha ha tashmisha lechud ve-ha tashmisha lechud. Here they are so
distinct in what functions they are serving that even though I'm intending
to sell you both, they require a separate act of קנין. kinyan.
Now of course that raises interesting questions. So if I try to
sell you a house plus a wheat field. Would that need separate
קניינים *kinyanim*? One is for grow wheat and the other is for
living, right? You know, I mean, where do you draw the line
here? I mean these are two commercial enterprises, so you might say
commercial enterprises are all one big thing. Let's say I was trying
to sell you a wheat field and an apple orchard, right? It's
like שמואל'ס *Shmuel's* statement sounds pretty all-inclusive. Sounds like it really doesn't
matter. Now he does say שדות *sadot*. A שדה *sade* is a...
is שדה *sade* limited to mean like a grain field? Right? So
you know, let's say I try to sell you, I have some
oil fields out in Texas and some orange orchards in California and
I'm going to... are those the same or are those different, right?
So it really raises these important, you know, a whole new question
here about what's considered to be in the same category. Okay, איכא
דאמרי *ika d'amri*, but thankfully we might not have to worry about
it because the conclusion of the גמרא *Gemara* is not this way.
איכא דאמרי אמר רב אמר רב נחמן החזיק בחוצית קנה מצובה *Ika
d'amri amar Rav amar Rav Nachman hechizik b'chusit kana m'tzuva*. So actually
if you take possession of the sand field it does work for
the pond. פשיטא *Peshita*! Isn't that obvious? דאמר שמואל מכר לו עשר
שדות *D'amar Shmuel machar lo eser sadot* etcetera. No, מהו דתימא התם
הוא דסדנא דארעא חד הוא *mahu d'teima hatam hu d'sadna d'ara chad
hu*. That's because it's all one big plot of land and it's
all the same type of thing. אבל הכא האי תשמישא לחווד והאי
תשמישא לחווד *Avel hacha hai tashmisha lechud vehai tashmisha lechud*. Here they're
different functions, so maybe you can't bundle them together. קמ"ל *Kamashma lan*
that you can. So in the conclusion of the גמרא *Gemara*, because
we normally assume we go by the second version, okay, we don't
have to worry how to define one category and two because the
גמרא *Gemara* is actually saying it really doesn't matter. Okay, but it
was an interesting attempt to distinguish. All
right, should maybe we'll just end here because we'll end a little
early, but rather than getting too far ahead of ourselves. Okay.